Hi and welcome back to another video
with it's Dr. Dan and today we're going
to be looking at limiting reactants or
also known as limiting reagents. So
whenever these are come you come across
these in stoeometry
this is always one of the trickiest
problems that you come across and how do
you know when you're going to see it?
Well, the whole idea is whenever you
have spe spe spe spe spe spe spe spe spe
spe spe spe spe spe spe spe spe spe spe
spe specific amounts of each reactant,
meaning that in your problem, all the
starting ingredients have either grams
associated with them or moles and they
actually have defined values. So why is
that important? Well, if you have a
chemical reaction, things can run out.
And that's what this is all about is
what what's going to run out first. So
for this type of reaction, what we're
going to be looking at is how we can
relate that to a common analogy. So what
we're going to look at is how
stochometry can be related to food
first.
Okay. So when we say we're going to be
looking at food, we're going to be
looking at how stokometry can be related
to making very specific amounts of
different recipes. So stochometry is
just like cooking. So if you're going to
be going through a different baking
exercise, reactants are just like
individual ingredients. So let's make a
cake. Let's actually go through that
entire process and actually see how we
can relate different chemical reactants
to something as simple as making food
which all of us do on a regular basis.
So if I'm going to have a cake recipe,
let's say if I have the following one.
So I have flour, one flour is going to
be mixed with three eggs and two milk
and that's going to create one cake. And
this is something that's very similar to
a chemical reaction. So, if we wanted to
write this out as a chemical reaction,
we could do that. We could say, okay,
well, we have one flour and that's going
to be combining with three eggs
and that's going to be combining with
two milk just like you would write out
any set of coefficients
with a chemical reaction. So, this is
all the same. So whenever you have any
type of chemical reaction, it's the same
thing as baking. So whenever you are
trying to bake at home or if you're
trying to cook, well, there's always
certain things that you tend to run out
of first and a lot of times it's eggs
and milk. So if we are to try to make
this, well, let's say I open my fridge
and I have all these different chemical
reactants available to me. Well, and I
want to be able to make as much cake as
possible because that's something that
of course we all want is something very,
very sweet and really enjoyable. So, if
I have all these pieces, well, how can
we try to look at this? Well, the whole
idea is to try to figure out exactly how
many cakes you can make. And being that
we have a specific recipe here. So, we
have one flour combined with three eggs
with two milk makes one cake, why don't
we try to see if we can do that? So, if
we take our ingredients and move them
around. So, why don't we have we have
our one flour that combines with three
eggs and that's also going to combine
with what? Two milk and that's one
individual ingredient. And then we also
can combine this over with another one
as well. So, one flour, three eggs, two
milk, and that all combines as well. So,
why don't we move all this over a little
bit? It all fits.
Now, what's left over over here? Well,
if I try to make a third cake, notice
how I'm out of milk and I have excess
amounts of both flour and eggs when
trying to write all this out. So if we
try to sort everything here into its
individual columns,
well, if I count all the original
starting ingredients that I have here,
well, you could see that, okay, we had
four milk, we had 10 eggs
and then we had four flour within this
particular what was in our kitchen. Now
in our recipe, we can only make so much
because certain things ran out. So once
we sorted everything into how many cakes
we can make, well this is a limiting
reagent problem. One thing that you saw
is that the milk it runs out by the
third cake. Meaning that milk in this
situation is referred to as a limiting
reagent. So what is that all about? How
can we define that? Well, a limiting
reactant is whatever the first reactant
that is used up first. Whip. We whip up
two cakes as a result, but we still have
a lot of leftover ingredients. So,
liming reagent once again is the first
reactant that's used up. Milk in this
situation ran out. By the third cake, we
did not have any milk left over. It all
ran out. It was used up. Now, when that
happens, when the limiting reactant is
used up, the reaction stops, meaning we
can't go any farther. The reaction
completely stops. So, when we whipped up
our first two cakes, we can't go
anymore. Even though we still have eggs
and flour left over that are ready and
willing to be made into something
delicious, there is no more left. So, in
this situation, the limiting reactant is
milk. And this is how you're going to be
defining this in different chemical
reactions. So limiting reactant is milk.
Now what other definitions that are very
crucial? The excess reactant is what is
left over after the reaction has already
stopped. So after we got to the second
cake, the reaction stopped because we
ran out of milk. Now being that that
completely stopped that means the
limiting reagent was all used up. Milk
was gone. So we had excess or leftover
amounts of flour and eggs left over. So
in the end we had the excess of two
flour and an excess of four eggs as a
result. Now is this something that we
can always try to relate this to? Well,
we're not always going to be sadly
cooking in chemistry class. A lot of
times we got to uh actually show this
with different chemical reactions and
different chemical species. So being
that that is said, why don't we go back
to the stoometry side and show how we
can relate this to specific amounts of
each reactant.
Back to chemistry. So now that's all
done. Now that we made our cakes, let's
try to relate how much of a instead of a
specific ingredient, how much of
specific reactant we can do in all of
our different ingredient in our
different recipes. So if I have instead
of a recipe, I have a reaction. So if I
have the following one, it says a
reaction creates methanol which is CH3
from carbon monoxide and hydrogen gas.
There are three moles of CO and 8 moles
of H2. What is the limiting reactant?
All right, so this is going to be very
similar to our cake recipe. How do we go
about doing it? Well, the very first
thing that we did is we had to lay out
our recipe, aka our chemical reaction.
So, our first step is what we're going
to be doing is writing our balanced
chemical equation. Now, this might
require a few skills that you may or may
not be comfortable with at this moment.
If that's the case, please try to review
the following. So, a couple little notes
here is make sure you're comfortable
with reading chemical names cuz that's
very common in general chemistry is that
you have to be able to convert from a
name to a formula. The other thing is
with names is that you might have to
swap drop. Meaning if you have an ionic
compound, you have to make sure you know
the balanced charges so that way you can
properly balance your chemical equation.
You also might need to be able to
predict the reaction as well. So keep in
mind that there are a lot of little tips
that you can have and I have videos on
every single one of these. I would
highly recommend checking them out to be
able to um brush up on those skills. Now
being though that this particular
chemical equation it it is mentioned in
the problem. So it's telling us that we
are creating methanol as a result. So
when we are actually making methanol all
right that's telling you that is your
product. So let's write that out. So our
product in this case is going to be
methanol. So CH3
O
and it's being created with carbon
monoxide and H2. Now when we have this
formula is it balanced? And one thing
you can probably see really quickly is
that okay well we have one carbon on
each side. Those are balanced. We have
one oxygen on each side. Those are
balanced. However, the hydrogens's
there's four four on the right hand side
and two on the two on the left hand
side, right? So, how can we easily
balance that is we can add a two here,
right? And now what is that exactly
showing? Well, it's going to show
something like this. So, this is what
it's going to look like. It's going to
have the following chemical reaction
here. So being that we have one carbon
monoxide reacting with two hydrogen
molecules that's going to be creating
one methanol. So it's very similar to
our recipe. This is the chemical
reaction we were going to follow. So
being that we were given a bunch of
starting ingredients, we can do some
little mole to mole calculations to try
to solve for what is going to be running
out in our chemical reaction. So let's
try to figure out using the amount of
each given reactant how we can calculate
how many moles or what the amount of
each product produced is. So if I have
my chemical reaction right we can see
that for every one mole of CO we have
two moles of hydrogen for all also for
every one mole of CO we create one mole
of methanol. So with all that starting
information, we were given that we had 3
moles of CO and 8 moles of hydrogen that
were going to be in this reaction. So
with that being said, let's bring that
down. So we had 3 moles
of CO
and then we also had 8 moles
of hydrogen. And our idea is here is we
want to see is what's going to run out
first. So what we can do is we can set
our up our little conversion table for
ourselves to see exactly how this is
going to run out just like our cake
recipe. So in our reaction what we have
is that for every 3 moles of CO I have
or sorry for every one mole of CO
I have one mole of CH3
O that is being created and the way that
we're seeing that is by looking directly
at the recipe. So we have 1 mo of CO is
creating 1 mole of CH3. Meaning that
when I convert this we do 3 * 1 mole of
CH3
/ 1 mo of CO and what we will get is 3
moles of CH3
is created. Now this what this
represents the story behind this
reaction is if all the three moles of CO
was used completely this is how many
moles of methanol we would make or aka
how many cakes are we making in this
recipe. Now what we're going to do is
we're going to do the same thing with
H2. So if I have reading my recipe, I
have 2 moles of H2
are equivalent to one mole of methanol.
Meaning that for every two moles of
hydrogen that react here or are baked,
we create one mole of of methanol. So
with that being said, what we can do is
we can summarize this chemical equation.
So what do I mean by summarize? Well,
what we're going to do is we can take 8
* 1 / 2. So if we do that, what we're
going to see is we're going to create
four moles of CH3
in our reaction. And notice how when we
do these two problems, our units are
canceling out. We're matching up all of
our units. Now, what do both of these
numbers tell you?
So the first time I said that if you use
up all three moles of CO, we create
three moles of methanol. The second one
tells you if you use up all eight moles
of hydrogen, we create four moles of
methanol. So what that tells you is what
is going to run out first. Well, being
that when we use up all of the CO, we
create less methanol. This is going to
run out. So as a result CO is our
limiting reactant
or our limiting reagent.
So being that that's our limiting
reactant also it might be abbreviated as
LR.
What is happening here is hydrogen is
going to be in excess. So your last step
here is identify the limiting reactant
which why is that important? Well, so
carbon monoxide is our limiting reactant
and like we mentioned, H2 is in excess,
meaning that there's going to be
leftovers.
So, whenever we are doing these types of
problems, there's a couple other little
tricks that we can do as well. So,
depending on what problem you're
presented in your chemistry class, you
could be asked some of the following
questions. Some of those could be how
much is left over calculated. how much
of that excess reactant was used. So how
much did you was required to go through
that specific reaction step or maybe you
have to do some further stoometry and
figure out the mass maybe the volume or
a couple different things like that. So
why don't we try and show a show one or
two of those examples. So if I had the
following information, we know that CO
ran out first. So the limiting reagent
is what governs how much excess is left
over. So being that we know that we used
up all three moles of CO, we can use
that to figure out how much hydrogen was
used. So if I set up that same chemical
equation, so 3 moles of CO and what we
want to do is figure out how much of our
hydrogen was actually used. So in our
original problem for every 1 mole of CO
we used 2 moles of hydrogen to react. So
when we do that math here we can see
that in the reaction it reacted with a
total of 6 moles of H2. So this is how
much was used in the reaction. So if we
wanted to figure out how much was left
over or how much is in excess, well
excess is always going to be the initial
minus what is used.
So in this case being that we started
with 8 moles of hydrogen
we are going to subtract that from the
six moles of hydrogen that was used to
figure out that oh we're going to have 2
moles of H2 left over. So the whole idea
is that when you have this excess
or leftovers it's the same thing going
back to our cake analogy from earlier.
So in the original problem from the
beginning, right, we had three we had
essentially four moles or four eggs left
over and we also had two two moles or
two things of flour that were left over
and those were in excess. But when we
looked at what was used in this
reaction, if we kind of go back to our
original recipe, well, you know that for
every three eggs were required for each
of these two cakes here. So that means
that six eggs were used. Or if we look
at the flower, well, we know that two
flour were used. So it's all about the
same type of information that is being
used within the problem. And it's all
about how do you look at it. Now when it
comes to the last step with stoeometry,
this is really where liming reagents can
get complicated and what's going to lead
to further videos. So depending on
really where this video was focusing on
was right here in the middle. The goal
is always the mole, meaning that we have
a chemical equation or a recipe and
we're converting it from moles to moles
and that will reveal the limiting
reagent. Now a lot of problems you might
have to calculate the grams that is
required meaning you have to use molar
mass to do that or if you have a
solution you might have to use marity to
get to that point or if you have a gas
you might have to use the ideal gas law
to get the lers. So, it all depends on
what type of problem you're being
presented, but the entire idea is to see
is what exactly ran out first in your
little recipe when you were trying to
bake your little cake or try to figure
out your chemical reaction. This has
been limiting reagents and there will be
future videos going through more
examples of these and also going through
the different types of stoometry.
There's already one video posted about
mass to mass. There's going to be more
coming soon. So, please feel free to
like and subscribe, and I hope to see
you back for future videos. Thank you so
much for watching. Bye now.